<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?>
<!DOCTYPE function SYSTEM "qtfmfunction.dtd">
<function name = "frenet" overload = "false">
<short>Frenet-Serret frames</short>
<syntax>[T, N1, N2, N3, J, K, L, M] = frenet(q)</syntax>
<long>
<para>
<code>frenet(q)</code>
computes the Frenet-Serret frames of a quaternion sequence or curve.
</para>
<para>
    Given a vector of quaternions (full or pure), representing a curve in
    3-space, 4-space or spacetime, this function computes the
    vectors of tangents, normals, binormals, and trinormals and the curvatures.
    The output parameters are as follows. The first four results are unit
    quaternions; the remaining four are scalars.
    <code>T</code> are the tangents;
    <code>N1</code> are the normals;
    <code>N2</code> are the binormals;
    <code>N3</code> are the trinormals;
    <code>J</code> is the moduli of the tangents,
    so that non-unit tangents are <code>J .* T</code>;
    <code>K</code> is the curvature; again <code>K .* N1</code>
    gives un-normalised normals;
    <code>L</code> is the second curvature or torsion;
    <code>M</code> is the third curvature or bitorsion.
</para>
<para>Note that the first and last values of <code>T</code> are not necessarily meaningful
because <code>T</code> is an approximation to the derivative, and therefore cannot be
correctly computed for the first and last values in <code>q</code>. The same applies
to <code>N1</code>, <code>N2</code> and <code>N3</code>,
but as these are computed using successive derivatives,
additional values at the extremities are not necessarily meaningful.
</para>
    <para>
        Comments on references: the article by Bharathi and Nagaraj was probably the first to
        explain the Frenet-Serret frames in 4-space using quaternions, but the
        Wikipedia article makes clear that Camille Jordan worked out the
        n-dimensional case in 1874. The article by Kurt Nalty is of value for its
        clear tutorial explanation of the formulae.
    </para>
</long>
<references>
    <reference>K. Bharathi and M. Nagaraj,
        'Quaternion Valued Function of a Real Variable Serret-Frenet Formula',
        <italic>Indian J. Pure and Applied Mathematics</italic>, <bold>18</bold>(6),
        507-511, June 1987.
    </reference>
    <reference>'Frenet-Serret formulas', subsection: 'Formulas in n dimensions',
        Wikipedia (English), accessed 27 April 2011.
        <www>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frenet%E2%80%93Serret_formulas</www>
    </reference>
<reference>Kurt Nalty,
'Trajectories and curves in 3 and 4 dimensions',
self-published article, 11pp, 19 January 2007, available at
<www>http://kurtnalty.com/</www>.
</reference>
</references>
</function>

<!--$Id: frenet.xml 1004 2017-11-15 17:14:09Z sangwine $-->
