<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?>
<!DOCTYPE function SYSTEM "qtfmfunction.dtd">
<function name = "imwrite" overload = "true">
<short>Write an image file from a quaternion array.</short>
<syntax>imwrite(A, filename, fmt)</syntax>
<long>
    <para>
        <code>imwrite</code> writes an image file from data stored in a pure
        quaternion array. It supports the same parameter profiles as the &matlab;
        function of the same name, but the first parameter must be a quaternion
        array with elements of type <code>uint8</code>,
        <code>uint16</code>, or <code>double</code>.
        The type of image written to the file depends on the
        quaternion data in the array <code>A</code>. If the quaternion data has
        components of type <code>uint16</code>, then 16-bit samples will be written to the
        file. In all other cases 8-bit data will be written to the file. <code>uint8</code> or
        <code>uint16</code> pixel values are not scaled - they are written directly to the
        image file. <code>double</code> or <code>single</code>
        pixel values are assumed to be in the range
        [0, 1] and are scaled by 255 before writing to the file. This behaviour
        follows from the behaviour of the overloaded &matlab; function which is used
        to write the image file after reformatting of the quaternion data into the
        form used by the &matlab; function.
    </para>
    <para>
        The function supports the same image file types as the &matlab; function.
    </para>
</long>
<examples>
<precode>
>> imwrite(randv(128), 'random.png')
</precode>
<para>
results in the creation of an image file like the result following.
In this case, because
<code>randv</code> generates <code>double</code> quaternion data with component values
in the range [0,1], the data is automatically scaled to the integer range
[0,255] before writing to the Portable Network Graphics file.
</para>
<figure>random.png</figure>
</examples>
<seealso>
<matlabfun name = "imwrite"/>
<qtfmfun name = "imreadq"/>
<qtfmfun name = "image"/>
</seealso>
</function>

<!--$Id: imwrite.xml 1004 2017-11-15 17:14:09Z sangwine $-->
