<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?>
<!DOCTYPE function SYSTEM "qtfmfunction.dtd">
<function name = "scatter3" overload = "true">
<short>3D scatter plot from quaternion array.</short>
<syntax>h = scatter3(q, varargin)</syntax>
<long>
    <para>
        <code>scatter3</code> plots a 3D scatter plot of elements in a 
        pure quaternion array. It supports the same parameter profiles as
        the &matlab; function of the same name, except that the first three
        parameters <code>(X, Y, Z)</code> are replaced by a single
        quaternion parameter, which must be a pure quaternion array.
    </para>
    <para>
        If two parameters are given and the second is 'rgb' or 'seq', a
        coloured scatter plot is produced. 'rgb' colours the plotted points
        according to the direction of the position vector of the point from 
        the origin using the convention of X = red, Y = green and Z = blue
        (the standard RGB colour space used in image processing).
        This is useful when the spatial position
        of points is of interest. 'seq' colours the points in a graded sequence
        of progressively darker values matching the sequence of points in the
        quaternion vector Q. This is useful when the ordering of the points is of
        interest.
    </para>
    <para>
        If more than one <code>varargin</code> parameter is given, or the first is
        neither 'rgb' nor 'seq', the <code>varargin</code> parameters are passed to the Matlab
        scatter3 function, and must therefore conform to the requirements of that
        function.
    </para>
    <para>
        The output parameter is optional, with the same functionality as
        the corresponding &matlab; function (a graphics handle).
    </para>
    <para>
        The axes are not labelled by this function.
        Use the standard &matlab; functions for this.
    </para>
    <para>
        For more sophisticated requirements, use the Matlab function
        and pass the X, Y and Z components of the quaternion array as the
        first three parameters.
    </para>
</long>
<examples>
<precode>
>> scatter3(randv(1,128), 'rgb'); axis equal
</precode>
<para>
results in the creation of the following plot.
</para>
<figure>scatter.png</figure>
</examples>
<seealso>
<qtfmfun name = "scatter4"/>
<qtfmfun name = "scatter4p3"/>
<matlabfun name = "scatter3"/>
</seealso>
</function>

<!--$Id: scatter3.xml 1004 2017-11-15 17:14:09Z sangwine $-->
