<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?>
<!DOCTYPE function SYSTEM "qtfmfunction.dtd">
<function name = "slerp" overload = "both">
<short>Spherical linear interpolation</short>
<syntax>y = slerp(q1, q2, t)</syntax>
<long>
<para>
<code>slerp(q1, q2, t)</code> interpolates between two quaternions
<code>q1</code> and <code>q2</code>,
using parameter <code>t</code> to determine how far along the 'arc'
between the two quaternions to position the result.
The function works in the same way for octonions.
</para>
<para>
<code>q1</code>, <code>q2</code>, and <code>t</code> must have the same size
unless one or more is scalar.
</para>
<para>
The third parameter, <code>t</code>, gives the 'distance' along the 'arc' between the
quaternions, 0 representing <code>q1</code> and 1 representing <code>q2</code>.
If <code>q1</code> and <code>q2</code> are
unit pure quaternions, the interpolation is along a great circle of the
sphere between the points represented by <code>q1</code> and <code>q2</code>.
If <code>q1</code> and <code>q2</code> are unit
full quaternions, the interpolation is along the 'arc' on the 4-sphere:
this means the result is a quaternion which represents a rotation
intermediate between the two rotations represented by <code>q1</code> and
<code>q2</code>. If the
first two parameters are not of unit modulus, then there is also
interpolation in modulus.
</para>
<para>
The third parameter may take values outside the range (0,1). Values within
this range will return results on the arc between the first two parameters.
Values outside the range will return results on the extension of the arc
outside the first two parameters (negative values being on the extension
beyond the first parameter, and values greater than 1 being on the extension
beyond the second parameter). Clearly, large values do not make sense, but
the code cannot check the validity of the values without computing the angle
between the two parameters, which would be a comparatively expensive check.
</para>
<para>
<code>q1</code> and <code>q2</code> are not restricted to be real.
</para>
<para>
The slerp function can be simply understood in terms of the ratio of two
vectors (pure quaternions). The ratio is the quaternion that rotates one
vector into the other. Taking a fractional power of this rotation and
then multiplying it by the first vector obviously gives a vector which is
part way along the arc between the two quaternions. The ratio is computed
using the multiplicative inverse. If the two quaternions are full, then
their ratio again gives a quaternion which multiplies one to give the
other, but this time in 4-space, including, if the moduli are not unity,
the scale factor needed to scale one into the other.
</para>
</long>
<examples>To interpolate between <code>qi</code> and <code>qj</code>,
we can supply a vector for <code>t</code>. The result shows that
when <code>t</code> is zero, the result is <code>qi</code>, and when
<code>t</code> is 1, the result is <code>qj</code>. At the mid-point of
the interpolation, we get <code>qi</code>/√2 + <code>qj</code>/√2, the
mid-point of the arc in 3-space:
<precode>
>> arc = slerp(qi, qj, [0:0.2:1])
 
arc = 1x6 quaternion array
 
>> show(arc)
 
arc.S = 0     0     0     0     0     0

arc.X = 1.0000    0.9511    0.8090    0.5878    0.3090    0.0000

arc.Y = 0    0.3090    0.5878    0.8090    0.9511    1.0000

arc.Z = 0     0     0     0     0     0
</precode>
</examples>
<seealso>
<qtfmfun name = "spherical_mean"/>
</seealso><references>
<reference>Ken Shoemake,
'Animating rotation with quaternion curves',
<italic>SIGGRAPH Computer Graphics</italic>,
<bold>19</bold> (3), July 1985, 245-254, ACM, New York, USA.
<doi>10.1145/325165.325242</doi>.
</reference>
</references>
</function>

<!--$Id: slerp.xml 1004 2017-11-15 17:14:09Z sangwine $-->
